MICHELE CLAIBOURN

I am a research director – a political scientist, data scientist, community-engaged scholar, and senior administrator - and professor with 20 years of experience teaching, leading, and managing research and data science teams.

My own work centers on action-based research, using the tools of data science to promote accountable governance, make visible racial and other social inequities, and impact public policy and movement building.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2021

Director of Equitable Analysis

The Equity Center, University of Virginia

- · Faculty, Batten School of Leadership and Public Policy, 2021-present
- · Faculty Affiliate & Lead Data Scientist, Global Policy Center, 2019-present
- · Co-Director, Community Policy, Analytics & Strategy Lab, 2018-present

2021 2015 Director, Research Data Services & Social, Natural, and Engineering Sciences UVA Library, University of Virginia

· Data Science Director, The Equity Center, 2020-2021 (partial buyout)

2015 2013 Director, StatLab and Research Data Services

UVA Library, University of Virginia

· Associate Director, Data Science Institute, 2014-2016 (partial buyout)

2013 2011

2011

2004

2004

2002

Data Scientist

Weldon Cooper Center for Public Service, University of Virginia

Assistant Professor

Department of Politics, University of Virginia

Assistant Professor

Department of Politics, University of Oklahoma



EDUCATION

2002 1996 PhD., Political Science

University of Wisconsin-Madison

Madison, WI

1993 1989

B.A. Political Science

Rice University

O Houston, TX



♣■ TEACHING AND MENTORING

2021 2002 **Graduate Courses**

University of Virginia and University of Oklahoma

· Imagining Equitable Policy, Public Interest Data Ethics & Practice, Data Visualization, Saving Lives with Data, Text as Data, Applied Causal Inference, General Linear Models, Linear Models, Applied Time Series, Mixed-Effects Models/Longitudinal Analysis, Introduction to Statistical Analysis

2020 2002 **Undergraduate Courses**

University of Virginia and University of Oklahoma

· Project First Gen +, Research Design & Analysis, The Presidency and the Public, Media & Political Communication, Political Pscyology & Decision Making, Citizen Competence in American Democracy, Introduction to American Politics

CONTACT

formal modern and modern formal modern forma

github.com/mclaibourn

in linkedin.com/in/mclaibourn

Project portfolio at mclaibourn.github.io.

Leadership

Envision, design, and lead research projects with academic and community partners seeking to understand racial and other disparities and to develop policy responses. Manage multiple projects and train and mentor students engaging in communityengaged data science.

Founded StatLab³, a data science consulting service for members of the UVA community. Built a new division within the library to support the growing data science research community at UVA, recruiting, hiring, and managing a team with diverse skills and talents

Have managed a team of 10-12 fulltime staff, 3-4 graduate fellows, and research teams across mulitple collaborations on a range of programmatic and research projects.

Methods and Software

Statistical modeling and data science R, RStudio, Shiny Data wrangling and visualization Stata and SPSS Text analytics GitHub and reproducibility Some Python and SQL Qualitative methods

	Ţ	
2020	i	Select StatLab Workshops⁴ University of Virginia
2013		Six-part series on Data Science in R, Multiple Imputation, Cluster Analysis, Duration Models, Matching Methods, Mixed-Effects Models, Sentiment Analysis, Topic Modeling, Text Classification, Data Wrangling, Linear Modeling
2019	•	REU Mentor
		School of Data Science, UVA
		SELECTED PUBLICATIONS AND PRESENTATIONS
2021		Albemarle County Equity Profile: Centering Equity in Evaluating Well-Being & Quality of Life for Albemarle County Resident ⁵
		The Equity Center, A UVA Democracy Initiative for the Redress of Inequity through Community-Engaged Scholarship and the Albemarle County Office of Equity and Inclusion
		· With Sam Powers, Michael Salgueiro, Siri Russell, Barbara Brown Wilson, and Alissa Ujie Diamond,
2019	•	Charlottesville Foster Care Study ⁶
		Report to the Charlottesville Department of Social Services
		With Charlotte McClintock and the Public Interest Data Lab
2021	•	Webinar, Mapping Inequity: Partnering for Data-Informed Decision Making International City/County Management Association
2020	•	Panelist, Racial Equity and Technology Public Interest Technology-University Network
2019		Panel Chair and Moderator Data & Democracy, School of Data Science Datapalooza, University of Virginia
2019		Homework and Hubris: Preparing for Community-Engaged Courses
2019	•	Homework and Hubris: Preparing for Community-Engaged Courses Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia
2019	•	
2019		Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia · With Paul Martin Confederate monuments and the history of lynching in the American South:
		Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia · With Paul Martin
		Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia · With Paul Martin Confederate monuments and the history of lynching in the American South: An empirical examination ⁷
		Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia · With Paul Martin Confederate monuments and the history of lynching in the American South: An empirical examination ⁷ Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences Oct 2021 · With Kyshia Henderson, Samuel Powers, Jazmin L. Brown-lannuzzi, and Sophie
2021		Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia · With Paul Martin Confederate monuments and the history of lynching in the American South: An empirical examination ⁷ Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences Oct 2021 · With Kyshia Henderson, Samuel Powers, Jazmin L. Brown-lannuzzi, and Sophie Trawalter Citizen Participation and Congressional Responsiveness: New Evidence for
2021		Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia · With Paul Martin Confederate monuments and the history of lynching in the American South: An empirical examination? Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences Oct 2021 · With Kyshia Henderson, Samuel Powers, Jazmin L. Brown-lannuzzi, and Sophie Trawalter Citizen Participation and Congressional Responsiveness: New Evidence for Why Participation Matters
2021		Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia · With Paul Martin Confederate monuments and the history of lynching in the American South: An empirical examination? Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences Oct 2021 · With Kyshia Henderson, Samuel Powers, Jazmin L. Brown-lannuzzi, and Sophie Trawalter Citizen Participation and Congressional Responsiveness: New Evidence for Why Participation Matters Legislative Studies Quarterly 38: 59-82 · With Paul Martin Creating Constituencies: Presidential Campaigns, Selective Mobilization, and the Scope of Conflict
2021		Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia · With Paul Martin Confederate monuments and the history of lynching in the American South: An empirical examination? Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences Oct 2021 · With Kyshia Henderson, Samuel Powers, Jazmin L. Brown-lannuzzi, and Sophie Trawalter Citizen Participation and Congressional Responsiveness: New Evidence for Why Participation Matters Legislative Studies Quarterly 38: 59-82 · With Paul Martin Creating Constituencies: Presidential Campaigns, Selective Mobilization, and the Scope of Conflict Political Behavior 34: 27-56
2021		Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia · With Paul Martin Confederate monuments and the history of lynching in the American South: An empirical examination? Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences Oct 2021 · With Kyshia Henderson, Samuel Powers, Jazmin L. Brown-lannuzzi, and Sophie Trawalter Citizen Participation and Congressional Responsiveness: New Evidence for Why Participation Matters Legislative Studies Quarterly 38: 59-82 · With Paul Martin Creating Constituencies: Presidential Campaigns, Selective Mobilization, and the Scope of Conflict
2021		Innovations in Teaching Pedagogy Summit, University of Virginia · With Paul Martin Confederate monuments and the history of lynching in the American South: An empirical examination? Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences Oct 2021 · With Kyshia Henderson, Samuel Powers, Jazmin L. Brown-lannuzzi, and Sophie Trawalter Citizen Participation and Congressional Responsiveness: New Evidence for Why Participation Matters Legislative Studies Quarterly 38: 59-82 · With Paul Martin Creating Constituencies: Presidential Campaigns, Selective Mobilization, and the Scope of Conflict Political Behavior 34: 27-56

Teaching and Writing

20+ years of experience teaching statistics and data science methods, policy, and political behavior to undergraduate and graduate students.

Design data workshop series for student and adult learning communities, including recruiting and mentoring instructors, marketing and assessment, and contributing to select topics.

Experienced writer in multiple formats, from university press books and peer-reviewed journal articles, to action-oriented reports for local and state agencies, educational materials, and informal writing.

Skilled in communicating about data, technology, and policy to stakeholders, advocates, and learners.

Last updated on 2021-12-13.

2007

The Third Face of Social Capital: How membership in Voluntary Associations Improves Policy Accountability

Political Research Quarterly 60: 192-201

· With Paul Martin

2002 | 2000

Gender Differences in Citizen-Level Democratic Citizenship: Evidence from the Comparative Study of Electoral Systems

Presented to the International Political Science Association (2000), the Midwest Political Science Association (2001), and the Conference on Comparative Study of Electoral Systems (2002)

- · With Virginia Sapiro
- · 2001 Winner, Sophonisba Breckenridge Award for best paper on Women & Politics, Midwest Political Science Association Annual Meeting

2000

Trusting and Joining: An Empirical Test of the Reciprocal Nature of Social Capital

Political Behavior 22: 267-291

· With Paul Martin



- 1. https://commpas.batten.virginia.edu/
- 2. https://virginiaequitycenter.github.io/cvilleequity_covid/
- 3. https://data.library.virginia.edu/statlab/
- 4: https://data.library.virginia.edu/training/past-workshops/
- 5. https://virginiaequitycenter.org/research/content/8306.
- 6. https://doi.org/10.18130/v3-ztey-hn31
- 7: https://www.pnas.org/content/118/42/e2103519118
- 8. https://www.press.uillinois.edu/books/catalog/75hhf7en9780252035920.html